Have you ever visited another country?
他の国を訪れたことはありますか？
Or, hey, have you ever seen a movie more than once?
それとも、映画を何度も見たことはありますか？
You know, we ask questions like these all the time,
こういった質問はよくしますよね。
and the secret to answering them like a native speaker
ネイティブのように答える秘訣は、
is something called the present perfect tense.
現在完了形というものです。
Now, I know, it can sound a little tricky,
ちょっと難しそうに聞こえるかもしれませんが、
but trust me, by the end of this explainer,
この説明が終わる頃には、
you're gonna be using it with total confidence
自信を持って使えるようになります。
to share all of your own awesome life experiences.
自分の素晴らしい経験を共有できるように。
So, take a look at this question.
この質問を見てみましょう。
Have you watched a movie three times? The really important thing here
映画を3回見たことがありますか？重要なのは、
is that it's not asking when you watched it.
いつ見たかを尋ねていないことです。
It doesn't care if it was last week or 10 years ago.
先週でも10年前でも関係ありません。
It's asking if this experience is a part of your life story right now.
今のあなたの人生の一部として、その経験があるかを問うています。
And that right there is the core idea of the present perfect.
これが現在完了形の核心です。
So let's break down exactly how it works. Here's our game plan.
では、具体的にどう機能するか見ていきましょう。
First, we'll get the main idea, this bridge to the present.
まず、主なアイデア、現在への架け橋を理解します。
Then we'll build the basic formula.
次に、基本的な公式を作ります。
After that, we'll learn how to count our experiences,
その後、経験の数え方を学び、
master two super important words, never and ever,
重要な2つの単語、neverとeverをマスターします。
And then of course, we'll put it all into practice.
そしてもちろん、実践に移します。
It's a simple five-step journey to get this down.
これを習得するためのシンプルな5ステップです。
Okay, first stop, we have to tackle
さて、最初のステップは、
the biggest thing that trips people up.
人々がつまずく大きなポイントに取り組むことです。
What is the real difference between the present perfect
現在完了形と過去形の違いは何でしょうか？
and the simple past? I mean, if you've ever gotten mixed up between
「I saw」と「I have seen」で混乱したことがあるなら、
I saw and I have seen, you are definitely not alone.
あなたは決して一人ではありません。
So let's make this crystal clear once and for all.
これをはっきりさせましょう。
Okay, check out the difference here.
ここでの違いを見てみましょう。
On the left, I visited the tower two years ago.
左側は「私は2年前に塔を訪れました」。
That's the simple past. It's a memory, a finished event.
これは過去形です。思い出で、完了した出来事です。
It's locked in time, but look at the right.
時間に固定されていますが、右側を見てください。
I have visited the tower three times.
「私は塔を3回訪れたことがあります」。
This is totally different, right? It's not about one single moment.
これは全く違いますよね？一瞬の出来事ではありません。
It's about the total experience that you carry with you now.
今持っている総合的な経験についてです。
Your past actions have basically created a fact about you today.
過去の行動が、今日のあなたに関する事実を作り出しています。
And this is the absolute best way to think about it.
これが最も良い考え方です。
The present perfect is a time bridge.
現在完了形は時間の架け橋です。
It literally takes something you did in the past
過去にしたことを、
and connects it to who you are in the present.
現在のあなたとつなげます。
It says, hey, this thing that happened before,
「以前に起こったことは、
it's still relevant, it still matters right now.
今も関連していて、重要です」と言っています。
So now that we get the why, let's jump into the how.
では、なぜを理解したので、次はどうするかに進みましょう。
And the good news, the basic formula
良いニュースは、基本的な公式が
for making these sentences is incredibly simple.
非常にシンプルだということです。
Let's take a look at the building blocks.
構成要素を見てみましょう。
And that's it, I'm not kidding.
これだけです、本当に。
The entire structure is just two parts. You take the word have or has,
全体の構造は2つの部分だけです。haveまたはhasを使い、
and you add the past participle of the verb. That's the whole thing.
動詞の過去分詞を加えます。それが全てです。
I have seen, you have played, she has eaten. See? Super simple.
「I have seen」、「you have played」、「she has eaten」。簡単ですよね。
Now there's just one tiny little exception to remember
ただし、覚えておくべき小さな例外があります。
and that's when to use has.
それはhasを使うタイミングです。
You just use has for the third person singular.
三人称単数の時だけhasを使います。
So if you're talking about he, she, it
だから、he、she、it、
or a specific person like Bob or my mother, you've got to use has.
またはBobや私の母のような特定の人について話すときは、hasを使います。
For example, my mother has visited Taiwan.
例えば、「私の母は台湾を訪れたことがあります」。
For everybody else, I, you, we, they, we just stick with have, easy.
他の全ての人、I、you、we、theyについては、haveを使います。簡単です。
Okay, so we've got the basic structure down.
さて、基本的な構造は理解できました。
Now let's add some detail.
次は詳細を加えましょう。
How do we talk about how many times we've done something?
何回何かをしたかをどう話すか？
This is where it gets really fun for telling stories.
ここから物語を語るのが本当に楽しくなる。
When we're counting experiences,
経験を数えるとき、
there are a couple of special words you just have to know.
知っておくべき特別な言葉がいくつかある。
For one time, we say once. For two times, it's twice.
一度のときは「once」、二度のときは「twice」。
And here's the best part. After that, it's a piece of cake.
そして、ここが一番のポイント。 それ以降は簡単だ。
You just use the number plus the word times,
数字に「times」をつけるだけ、
three times, four times, a billion times.
三回、四回、無限大回。
Just remember that these words usually go
これらの言葉は通常、
at the very end of the sentence.
文の最後に置くことを覚えておいて。
So yeah, just burn this into your memory.
だから、これをしっかり覚えておこう。
Once and twice are the two special ones.
「once」と「twice」が特別なものだ。
Get those down and the rest is just simple counting.
これを覚えれば、あとは単純な数え方だ。
It's a fantastic little shortcut to sound way more natural.
自然に聞こえる素晴らしいショートカットだ。
Here we go, a perfect example. I have met the singer once.
さあ、完璧な例を見てみよう。 私はその歌手に一度会った。
You see how it works? We've got our formula.
どういうことかわかる？ 私たちの公式がある。
Have, plus the past participle, met,
「have」と過去分詞の「met」を使って、
and then we just pop our frequency word once
その後に頻度の言葉「once」を
right there at the end to say how many times.
文の最後に置いて、何回かを示す。
And here's another one, putting all our rules together.
そして、もう一つ、すべてのルールを組み合わせる。
My mother has visited Taiwan twice. Why has?
私の母は台湾に二度訪れた。 なぜ「has」なのか？
Well, because my mother is third person singular. And why twice?
それは母が三人称単数だから。 なぜ二度なのか？
Because it happened two times. See, everything just clicks into place.
それは二回起こったから。 ほら、すべてがうまくいく。
It's perfect. All right, let's level up our game.
完璧だ。さて、次のレベルに進もう。
We know how to talk about things we've done,
私たちは自分がしたことについて話せるが、
but what about things we haven't done?
まだしていないことについてはどうする？
Or how do we ask other people about their experiences?
他の人の経験についてどう聞く？
This is where two powerful little words come into play.
ここで二つの強力な言葉が登場する。
Never and ever. This slide shows you the two sides of the same coin.
「never」と「ever」。このスライドは同じコインの両面を示している。
On the left, we use never to say we have zero experience.
左側では「never」を使って、 経験がゼロであることを示す。
I have never eaten sushi. It means not once, not ever.
私は寿司を一度も食べたことがない。 それは一度も、決してないという意味。
Then on the right, we use ever to ask a question,
右側では「ever」を使って質問する。
to ask if something has happened at any point in someone's life.
誰かの人生の中で何かが起こったかを尋ねる。
Have you ever climbed a mountain? So just to be super clear,
あなたは山に登ったことがありますか？ だから、はっきり言うと、
never is your go-to word when you wanna say zero times.
「never」はゼロ回と言いたいときの基本の言葉。
You just slot it right between half and the past participle.
それを「have」と過去分詞の間に入れる。
I have never been to Paris. It's such a strong, clear way to say
私はパリに行ったことがない。 それはその経験がないことを強く示す。
you haven't had that experience. And ever is like a magic key.
「ever」は魔法の鍵のようなもの。
It's the key that unlocks questions about someone's whole life.
誰かの人生全体に関する質問を開く鍵だ。
When you ask, have you ever, you're asking about everything
「have you ever」と尋ねると、 彼らが生まれた日から今までのすべてを聞いている。
from the day they were born up until this very second.
素晴らしい会話を始めるための完璧なツールだ。
It is the perfect tool for starting a great conversation.
さて、理論は一つのことだが、
Okay, theory is one thing,
実践がすべてを定着させる。
but practice is where it all starts to stick.
新しい英語のツールのすべての要素を作った。
We've built all the pieces of our new English tool
今、それを実際に使う時だ。
and now it's time to actually use it.
これらの文を組み立てられるか見てみよう。 君ならできる。
Let's see if you can put these sentences together. You got this.
さあ、最初の問題。 君の言葉は「you」「have」「ever」「played」。
All right, first one up. Your words are you, have, ever, and played.
これらをどう並べて、誰かに ギターを弾いたことがあるか尋ねる？ 少し考えてみて。できた？
How would you arrange those to ask someone
正解は「have you ever played the guitar？」 素晴らしい！
if they've played the guitar? I'll give you a second. Got it?
さて、次に進もう。
The correct answer is have you ever played the guitar? Nicely done.
今度はメキシコ料理を食べたことについて尋ねる。
Okay, you're on a roll. Let's do the next one.
言葉は「you」「have」「eaten」「ever」。 どう組み合わせる？
This time we're asking about eating Mexican food.
準備はいい？ 正しい質問は「have you ever eaten Mexican food？」
The words are you, have, eaten, ever. How do they fit together?
素晴らしい！ 最後の挑戦に行こう。
You ready? The right question is, have you ever eaten Mexican food?
今度は質問ではなく、 文を作りたい。
Fantastic! And for our final challenge,
ジグソーパズルを買ったことがないと言いたい。
let's make a statement instead of a question.
言葉は「never」「have」「I」「bought」。
You wanna say that you have zero experience buying a jigsaw puzzle.
順番を考えてみて。
Your words are, never, have, I, and bought.
答えは「I have never bought a jigsaw puzzle」。 完璧だ！
So let's do a super quick recap of everything.
では、すべてを簡単に振り返りましょう。
First, remember the present perfect is that time bridge from your past to your present.
まず、現在完了形は過去から現在への時間の架け橋です。
The formula is just have or has, plus the past participle.
その公式は、haveまたはhasに過去分詞を加えます。
We count with special words, like once and twice.
特別な言葉、例えばonceやtwiceを使います。
We say zero experience with never, and we ask about any experience with ever.
経験がないときはneverを使い、経験があるか尋ねるときはeverを使います。
That's the whole thing.
これが全てです。
And you know, if you take just one thing away from all this, let it be this.
もし一つだけ覚えておくなら、これを忘れないでください。
The present perfect is so much more than just a grammar rule from a textbook.
現在完了形は教科書の文法ルール以上のものです。
It's a tool for storytelling.
物語を語るためのツールです。
It's how you share the moments and experiences that have actually shaped who you are today.
あなたが今日の自分を形作った瞬間や経験を共有する方法です。
That's how you tell the story of your life.
それがあなたの人生の物語の語り方です。
And that brings us to a final thought for you.
最後に、考えてほしいことがあります。
I want you to actually think about this question.
この質問について実際に考えてみてください。
What is one interesting thing you have done in your life? See that?
あなたの人生で行った面白いことは何ですか？これが重要です。
You can use this grammar right now to answer that very question.
今すぐこの文法を使って、その質問に答えられます。
Thanks so much for joining me for this explainer.
この解説に参加してくれてありがとうございます。
Now go out there and keep building your story.
さあ、外に出てあなたの物語を築き続けてください。